<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.7">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/howto/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/howto/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-07-04T01:23:13+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/howto/feed.xml</id><title type="html">how to</title><entry><title type="html">how to narrate transparently</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/howto/narrate-transparently" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="how to narrate transparently" /><published>2023-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-04T01:21:59+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/howto/narrate-transparently</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/howto/narrate-transparently"><![CDATA[<p>I read half of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Executioner%27s_Song">The Executioner’s Song</a> – Norman Mailer’s gargantuan, Pulitzer Prize-winning nonfiction novel about Gary Gilmore – and figured I could put it down and move on.</p>

<p>I knew how the story would end and had read enough of the book to appreciate Mailer as a writer.
And yet, despite my skepticism of <a href="https://okjuan.medium.com/feeling-good-about-ditching-books-1c4633fd87f">the value of finishing books</a>, a few months on I found myself drawn back in.
And in my second session with the book I noticed a technique that Mailer uses throughout it.</p>

<p>I don’t know if the technique has a name.
A good name might be <strong>transparent narrator</strong>.
Its purpose is to convey a character’s point of view without quoting them or otherwise indicating that you are speaking for them.</p>

<p>Here’s a passage from Mailer’s book, concerning Tamera, a cub reporter who began working on Gary’s story before it became world-famous:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Tamera had gone to work at 5 A.M. and spent six hours Xeroxing Gary’s letters. She knew some of the reporters were raising their eyebrows at how she protected the stuff, but Tamera didn’t want anyone reading over her shoulder, and making the sort of cynical nonchalant comments newspaper people could make. Still, nobody seemed that excited.</p>

  <p>In fact, at the Friday afternoon meeting, the Executive Editor said, “I don’t think we’re interested in love letters.” Just brushed it off like that.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The narrator gives us a sense of Tamera’s personality and attitude towards the situation without quoting her or breaking the third person narrative.
The narrator is not pretending to be Tamera, and yet we hear her <em>through</em> him, most clearly in the brief sentences that punctuate both paragraphs:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Still, nobody seemed that excited.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Just brushed it off like that.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>These phrases are said by the narrator in Tamera’s voice.
We feel like she is telling us her part of the story over a cup of coffee.</p>

<p>Mailer achieves this effect by embedding many little phrases along the away.
Notice the casualness of this phrase:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>reporters were raising their eyebrows at how she protected the stuff</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>The stuff</strong>, in particular.</p>

<p>Notice the casualness here too:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>the sort of cynical nonchalant comments newspaper people could make</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>Newspaper people</strong>.</p>

<p>These are consistent, subtle choices that change how the reader perceives the story.
This technique is crucial to keeping Mailer’s 1,000+ page book fresh.
If the whole thing was written from his perspective, it would be much harder to get through.
Instead, he narrates transparently, allowing us to hear the story from the perspective of the many people who lived it.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="narration" /><category term="point-of-view" /><category term="norman-mailer" /><category term="new-journalism" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I read half of The Executioner’s Song – Norman Mailer’s gargantuan, Pulitzer Prize-winning nonfiction novel about Gary Gilmore – and figured I could put it down and move on.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">how to like your life</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/howto/like-your-life" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="how to like your life" /><published>2023-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-04T01:21:59+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/howto/like-your-life</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/howto/like-your-life"><![CDATA[<p>This morning I almost got overwhelmed with things I had to do.
Like when you set your glass down too hard and the wave rises to the rim menacingly.</p>

<p>I took a deep breath and I wrote the things down – things I had to do at work, things I had to do for my upcoming marriage, and things I had to do to enjoy Toronto, where I am for the week.
Each of these categories overflows with things I could do, as I guess any category does.</p>

<p>I wrote only a few things per category and recognized immediately that this was the whole day ahead of me.
If I completed everything on the list, I would have good reason to be pleased.
And yet there was so little on it.</p>

<p>I recoil with something like disgust when I look at my day on paper.
That’s it?
These things?
So I avoid writing down my daily activities, even if I know what I intend to do.
I proceed jauntily as if my day were big enough to contain all its possibilities, the million different days it could be.
But I know it’s only one day, which is but one measly little trickle mocking my thirst for experience and accomplishment.</p>

<p>But I suspect that this exercise, like other painful ones, offers the opportunity to grow.
Write the list and look at it.
What is so ugly about it?
Is it these particular activities?
Do you wish you weren’t spending your life doing them?
This is an answer to know and confront.</p>

<p>But if these activities are good, if they satisfy your expectations of life-worthy activities, then why don’t they satisfy you?
Is their ugliness your own mortality being reflected back at you?
Will you <a href="/howto/live-in-the-moment">make peace with it</a>?</p>

<p>Or is their ugliness coming from their will to control you?
Does it make you squirm to think that you have handed over the reigns?
If you wrote this same list in past tense at the end of the day, would it look more appealing?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="time-management" /><category term="mortality" /><category term="mindfulness" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This morning I almost got overwhelmed with things I had to do. Like when you set your glass down too hard and the wave rises to the rim menacingly.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">how to revise a sentence (2)</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/howto/revise-a-sentence-2" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="how to revise a sentence (2)" /><published>2023-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-04T01:21:59+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/howto/revise-a-sentence-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/howto/revise-a-sentence-2"><![CDATA[<p>Take this quote by anthropologist Clifford Geertz:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>One of the most significant facts about humanity may finally be that we all begin with the natural equipment to live a thousand kinds of life but end in the end having lived only one.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A lovely little idea weighed down by free-loading filler words.
First of all, the preamble is unnecessary.
<strong>We all</strong> alone indicates we are talking about humans.
And let us decide how significant your fact is.
Don’t be so insecure (or arrogant).</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><del>One of the most significant facts about humanity may finally be that</del> We all begin with the natural equipment to live a thousand kinds of life but end in the end having lived only one.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>How good is a sentence if decapitation improves it?</p>

<p>The other necessary change is screamingly obvious.
We <strong>end in the end</strong>?
Sure, but only after we have begun in the beginning.
(Was he trying to reach a word count? Or distract a doorman while someone snuck in?)</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We all begin with the natural equipment to live a thousand kinds of life but <del>end</del> in the end <del>having lived</del> live only one.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>For our troubles, we get a free upgrade from <strong>having lived</strong> to <strong>live</strong>.
Free the verb to be a verb.</p>

<p>We’ve chopped our way down to the meat of the sentence.
Is there any fat to trim?</p>

<p>Is <strong>We all</strong> better than <strong>We</strong>?</p>

<p>How much better is <strong>kinds of life</strong> than <strong>lives</strong> that it deserves three times the space?
Sentence space is precious.
Raise the rent.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We <del>all</del> begin with the natural equipment to live a thousand <del>kinds of life</del> lives but in the end <del>having lived</del> live only one.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Can we prune more?
Riding the high of halving the original, it’s tempting to cut out <strong>in the end</strong>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We begin with the natural equipment to live a thousand lives but <del>in the end</del> live only one.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>But <strong>in the end</strong> is contributing.
It invokes the passage of time by drawing a line from <strong>begin</strong>.
It draws the arc of a single life lived.
Tracing this line we sense the transformation of many possibilities into one reality.
We also sense the briefness of this single life now that the sentence is briefer.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We begin with the natural equipment to live a thousand lives but in the end live only one.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There are several words here doing a job.
<strong>Natural equipment</strong> means bodily and mental potential, while <strong>equipment</strong> alone would mean material tools like hammers and textbooks.</p>

<p>The <strong>the</strong> in front of <strong>natural equipment</strong> is one of those pesky ones.
It’s like a plain, mild-mannered friend that you think you can exclude from the group but without whom things are somehow less comfortable.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We begin with <del>the</del> natural equipment to live a thousand lives but in the end live only one.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>When we scrutinize words like this, when we interrogate them, we learn what each of them is doing.
This allows us not only to eliminate useless words but to replace imprecise ones.</p>

<p>Is <strong>a thousand lives</strong> enough?
Should we multiply it with itself to raise the stakes?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We begin with the natural equipment to live a million lives but in the end live only one.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Hmm.
Now it feels too… flippant?
And somehow… overstated?</p>

<p>A <strong>thousand lives</strong> has the modesty that lacked in the original sentence’s preamble.
It sticks the landing without too extravagant a flourish.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We begin with the natural equipment to live a thousand lives but in the end live only one.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Much better.
Ok, next sentence.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="editing" /><category term="writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Take this quote by anthropologist Clifford Geertz: One of the most significant facts about humanity may finally be that we all begin with the natural equipment to live a thousand kinds of life but end in the end having lived only one.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">how to interpret your dreams</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/howto/interpret-your-dreams" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="how to interpret your dreams" /><published>2023-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-04T01:21:59+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/howto/interpret-your-dreams</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/howto/interpret-your-dreams"><![CDATA[<p>Freud, apparently, thought dreams prevented us from going crazy.</p>

<p>According to him, dreams are expressions of the desires and fears we don’t dare face in waking life, facets of ourselves that we repress like a child smothers a ball under the surface of a pool.
And, in the dark of night, dreams relieve the pressure by playing out these urges.
Were they not allowed these covert outings, but blocked and pushed indefinitely, they would eventually burst through the surface and rupture our psyche.
And so dreams are the release valve for the unrelenting force our unconscious exerts to have its will expressed.</p>

<p>This idea intrigued a young William Dement and launched him into a trailblazing career in sleep science.
Could he use science to prove Freud’s theory right?
REM sleep, which Dement discovered, seemed promising.
Studies proved it to be both indispensable and the only part of sleep when dreaming occurred.</p>

<p>And there was the case of a radio personality suffering a mental breakdown during his <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Tripp">201-hour “wakeathon”</a>, in which he broadcasted, without sleep, for a week straight.
Why did he start hallucinating and dissociating?
Was it just the drugs he took to stay awake, or could it have been the absence of dreams, which would have helped keep his psyche in balance?
Dr. Dement’s faith in Freud’s theory finally faltered after accompanying a high school senior’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Randy_Gardner_sleep_deprivation_experiment">record-breaking sleepless marathon</a> of eleven days and witnessing nothing much worse than acute fatigue and acute crankiness.</p>

<p>Some scientists have claimed the opposite to Freud’s theory – that dreams not only do nothing but mean nothing.
They are a random side-effect of the brain function that produces them, a periodic electric signal that occurs right before and during REM sleep.
Our eyes move rapidly and we experience absurd scenarios because electricity is coursing through our neural network like water splashing over rocks.
But, as Dement points out, even if the ripples of electricity start out with no intended destination, their traversal is influenced by pathways carved out by our thoughts and behaviors.
In the same way that water trickling down the face of a rock follows paths determined by the rock’s shape and texture, our dreams depend on the paths our neurons allow electrical signals to traverse.
The meaning of a dream comes from our neural connections, which we wired and rewired continuously throughout our life.</p>

<p>Dreams have things to tell us, whether or not all scientists agree.
It is an ordinary thing to dream about things that came up during the day.
In his essay <a href="https://nautil.us/the-kekul-problem-236574/">The Kekulé Problem</a>, Cormac McCarthy considers the curious phenomenon of problem-solving while sleeping, with particular interest on why solutions are presented mysteriously as images and not in plain language.
He offers a clever answer: the brain is old, but language is new.
And, just like we prefer to communicate in our native tongue, our brain prefers to express itself through imagery.</p>

<p>But this idea, stirring as it is, might be no more accurate than Freud’s.
In his book <a href="https://eagleman.com/books/livewired/">Livewired</a>, neuroscientist David Eagleman proposes a theory of dreams that suggests a rather different answer to the Kekulé Problem.
He proposes that the brain activity responsible for dreams, which targets the parts of the brain typically used for vision, exists to maintain our sense of sight.
Without this scheduled strengthening exercise, it could be overtaken by other, neuron-hungry brain processes that don’t depend on light of day to stay active.
If this is true, then the answer to the Kekulé Problem is less mysterious.
Dreams are visual because their machinery is.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="dreams" /><category term="subsconscious" /><category term="psychosis" /><category term="sanity" /><category term="science" /><category term="neuroplasticity" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Freud, apparently, thought dreams prevented us from going crazy.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">how to understand the world</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/howto/understand-the-world" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="how to understand the world" /><published>2023-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-04T01:21:59+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/howto/understand-the-world</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/howto/understand-the-world"><![CDATA[<p>Several years ago, in the last and lightest semester of my Computer Science degree, I spent a good deal of my free time studying YouTube videos about politics, philosophy, and sociology.</p>

<p>One of my favorites was Professor Raymond Geuss’s lecture on the process of <a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/alienation/">Alienation</a>.
In it he distinguishes between two kinds of frameworks: <strong>normative</strong> and <strong>evaluative</strong>.
Both are frameworks for understanding the world, models that simplify a wild, diverse world into a manageable set of rules and components.</p>

<p>However, only the <strong>normative</strong> ones claim that their rules and components are in reality’s underlying skeleton.
<strong>Evaluative</strong> frameworks are humbler.
They offer you rules and components that, while they help in <em>understanding</em> the world, don’t claim to decode its blueprint.
They just help you sketch a good picture.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="philosophy" /><category term="poli-sci" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Several years ago, in the last and lightest semester of my Computer Science degree, I spent a good deal of my free time studying YouTube videos about politics, philosophy, and sociology.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">how to revise a sentence</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/howto/revise-a-sentence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="how to revise a sentence" /><published>2023-05-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-04T01:21:59+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/howto/revise-a-sentence</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/howto/revise-a-sentence"><![CDATA[<p>Suppose you have this sentence:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>It leads us out of the present, leading to a life spent leaning into the future</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Conventional writing wisdom would condemn it for using <strong>leads</strong> and <strong>leading</strong> in the same sentence.
But, more importantly, it doesn’t sound right.</p>

<p>What if we prune <strong>leading</strong> out of the second part of the sentence?</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>It leads us out of the present, into a life spent leaning into the future</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Now there’s a bit of tension around the comma.
You can hear a touch of awkwardness when you read it aloud to yourself.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It leads us out of the present and into a life spent leaning into the future</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Is that better?
Or is there is still something off?
If you’re not sure, leave it for now and read through the draft later.</p>

<p>In the words of writer <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/13155290">Verlyn Klinkenborg</a>: <em>Read until your ear detects a problem - a subtle disturbance. Stop there.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="editing" /><category term="writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Suppose you have this sentence: It leads us out of the present, leading to a life spent leaning into the future]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">how to come up with ideas (2)</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/howto/come-up-with-ideas-2" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="how to come up with ideas (2)" /><published>2023-04-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-04T01:21:59+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/howto/come-up-with-ideas-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/howto/come-up-with-ideas-2"><![CDATA[<p>I find it surprisingly easy to whistle a new tune.
It will sound like songs I’ve heard before, but never the same.
And yet it is desperately indebted to music I’ve heard before.</p>

<p>Our memory is conveniently inaccurate.
When we remember something, we don’t retrieve it from storage, but redraw it by tracing points scattered around our brain.
(Here I am, trying to recollect descriptions faithfully from Antonio Damasio’s <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/103867.Descartes_Error?from_search=true&amp;from_srp=true&amp;qid=resxWaFOq4&amp;rank=1">Descartes’ Error</a>.)</p>

<p>Exposing yourself to new ideas and images is crucial for the development of your creative vocabulary.
Quite easily the tokens you pocket on your detours offer themselves as embellishments or examples for your work back home.
And sometimes you encounter something greater – a new way of thinking that pierces like an axis into a new dimension.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="creativity" /><category term="memory" /><category term="psychology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I find it surprisingly easy to whistle a new tune. It will sound like songs I’ve heard before, but never the same. And yet it is desperately indebted to music I’ve heard before.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">how to motivate yourself</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/howto/motivate-yourself" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="how to motivate yourself" /><published>2023-04-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-04T01:21:59+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/howto/motivate-yourself</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/howto/motivate-yourself"><![CDATA[<p>The idea is that, through sheer thought, you can mobilize a body sapped of motivation.
Willpower is like <a href="https://youtu.be/TuEdU_lrtZk">the secret gas</a> in your car that hides below the E on the fuel gauge.
Except it never runs out.
Mind over matter.</p>

<p>But isn’t the heroic surge of energy released from this mental trapdoor merely motivation?
Sure, you’ve had to rummage and claw for it, but what is it if not motivation?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="psychology" /><category term="motivation" /><category term="work" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The idea is that, through sheer thought, you can mobilize a body sapped of motivation. Willpower is like the secret gas in your car that hides below the E on the fuel gauge. Except it never runs out. Mind over matter.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">how to live in the moment</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/howto/live-in-the-moment" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="how to live in the moment" /><published>2023-03-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-04T01:21:59+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/howto/live-in-the-moment</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/howto/live-in-the-moment"><![CDATA[<p>It is old advice to live now because now is the only time you will ever live.
Embrace this moment because it is the only one in reach.
But the advice resonates only so deeply with me.
I find many nows made for trading, worthy of giving up for what I can get later.</p>

<p>To this cliche <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/54785515">Oliver Burkeman</a> adds a darker harmony with a note of his own.
You will never make the most of your time.
It is painfully short and any bid for optimal use of it is doomed.
Suddenly the original cliche is not about changing your attitude but about accepting that you get what you get.
The task is not about settling, but about admitting defeat.
Time rules you and the freest you can get is by giving up the fight.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="time-management" /><category term="mortality" /><category term="mindfulness" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It is old advice to live now because now is the only time you will ever live. Embrace this moment because it is the only one in reach. But the advice resonates only so deeply with me. I find many nows made for trading, worthy of giving up for what I can get later.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">how to coordinate metaphors</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/howto/coordinate-metaphors" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="how to coordinate metaphors" /><published>2023-03-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-04T01:21:59+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/howto/coordinate-metaphors</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/howto/coordinate-metaphors"><![CDATA[<p>It’s important to keep your metaphors from bumping into one another.</p>

<p>Take this passage from Oliver Burkeman’s book <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/54785515-four-thousand-weeks">Four Thousand Weeks: Time Management for Mortals</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>…most of us were raised [to] prioritize future benefits over current enjoyments. But ultimately it backfires. It <strong>wrenches</strong> us out of the present, leading to a life spent <strong>leaning</strong> into the future, worrying about whether things will work out…</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If we are <strong>wrenched</strong> out of the present, how are we only <strong>leaning</strong> into the future?
Wouldn’t we be <strong>thrown</strong> into it?</p>

<p>To coordinate these two metaphors, we need to change the word <strong>wrenches</strong> or the word <strong>leaning</strong>.
(Or both.)
The image of being <strong>wrenched out of the present</strong> is vivid, but I find the image of <strong>leaning into the future</strong> more precise.</p>

<p>Burkeman could’ve chosen a word other than <strong>wrenches</strong> to lead better into the image of <strong>leaning</strong>.
Possibilities include: <strong>pushes</strong>, <strong>nudges</strong>, <strong>tips</strong>, <strong>pulls</strong>, <strong>shifts</strong>.
We are not limited to physicality, either: action words like <strong>coaxes</strong> and <strong>lures</strong> are also viable.</p>

<p>We can’t use <strong>leads</strong> because that would clash with <strong>leading</strong> in the second part of the sentence.
(Although, if we really liked <strong>leads</strong> as a replacement for <strong>wrenches</strong>, we could <a href="/howto/revise-a-sentence">revise the sentence</a> to accomodate it.)</p>

<p>To pick a solution, test it against the problem.
You know you’ve found a solution when the two images flow into each other or click into place like neighboring puzzle pieces.</p>

<p>If you enjoy analyzing sentences closely like this, check out the last section of <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/13155290">Several Short Sentences About Writing</a>, where Klinkenborg considers “Some Practical Problems” with sentences written by his students.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="imagery" /><category term="cohesiveness" /><category term="writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s important to keep your metaphors from bumping into one another.]]></summary></entry></feed>